Tamara Paula Temple

Webologist and Software Craftsperson

+1-651-485-2195⊠ tamara@tamouse.org https://tamouse.org **y** tamouse tamouse

Summary

Deeply experienced in software design and development methodologies, especially related to the disciplines of software quality, web applications, user experience, and team building. Presently working at the intersection of Rails, GraphQL, and React, developing modern web applications with fast response times.

web libraries

Skills

general software engineering, web development, business analysis, consulting, facilitatengineering

ing, teaching

software architecture, full-stack, backend, fron-

tend, low-level design, coding, debugging, testing, tool chains, APIs: SOAP,

REST, GraphQL

Rails, Sinatra, Django, Flask, Express, frameworks

ApolloServer, JAMstack, Gatsby

databases PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQLite, Mon-

goDB, Redis

languages Ruby, JavaScript, Perl, Shell, Python 3, PHP, HTML5, CSS3, SCSS/SASS,

React, GraphQL, ApolloClient

HAML, C/C++

servers Netlify, nginx, puma, AWS ECS, EBS,

S3, Cloudfront

tools Node.js, Emacs, Webstorm, RubyMine, rake, thor, yeoman (yo), webpack, ba-

bel, npm/npx, gulp, make

static site jekyll, middleman, gatsby

generators

testing Minitest, RSpec, Jest, Testing Library

Program architecture and design; User-/task-centered design; Test-/behaviour-driven development; Methods Structured analysis, design, development, and testing; Process flow analysis, systems theory, cybernetics; Object-oriented analysis, design, programming, and testing; Agile development, scrum master; Continuous everything: integration, testing, deployment; Precision elicitation and facilitation, communication for action

Education

1975-1980 Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, 3.2 GPA.

Additional Structured analysis, design, programming and testing, System testing, Objected oriented analysis, design, programming and testing, Consulting and facilitating skills, Neurolinguistic programming certified practitioner, Project management, Public speaking and presentation skills, You Don't Know JS with Kyle Simpson, Advanced JavaScript, Numerous courses through FrontendMasters.com on React, Webpack, GraphQL, JAMstack, Angular, others

Experience

2001-present Web Developer, Pontiki Software Crafts, Mendota Heights, Minnesota.

Freelance web design and development, including pro bono work for non-profits and individuals desiring a presence on the Web. Includes finding hosting space, development of information architecture, design layout of site, development and/or repurposing of content, and maintenance.

- User experience and User-centered design for interactive web sites
- Database design for dynamic web sites and applications
- Creation and developing on frameworks for generating static web sites
- Frameworks and infrastructure to implement business logic and web site features
- Environments and tools for development, testing, integration and deployment
- Teach and coach new developers, running "Toast & Tech" study groups
- O Volunteer mentor/coach/instructor for Women Who Code Twin Cities, Hack-the-Gap, Code Switch (Code for America)

2017-2020 API-driven Rubyist, React/GraphQL Maven, ReachLocal (Gannett), Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Software engineering across the entire Kickserv application stack from the back end in Ruby on Rails with a Postgresql database, implementing a GraphQL server controller with various queries, types, mutations, and resolvers to implement a GraphQL API, and create a React front end that consumes that GraphQL API with Apolloclient in order to replace the legacy JavaScript code from over a decade of various implementation styles and libraries, giving a modern, cohesive approach to front end web application development.

- o provide queries, mutations, types, and resolvers that call Rails ActiveRecord and ActiveModel models to create, read, update, and destroy records as necessary for the operation of the application.
- o architect and develop the JavaScript front end code in React to provide a good separation of concerns ensuring testability and writing tests where none existed prior; lowering maintenance costs, and ensuring easy replaceability to enable new features to be added with less overall effort and more predictability.
- o build Rails models, controllers, views, and React components for new Kickserv features.
- o rewrite several legacy JavaScript and ¡Query files into cohesive React component trees.
- o implement various POROs (Plain Old Ruby Objects) to extract complicated and repeated code from controllers into testable and repurposeable units, including service objects for interfacing with third party APIs.
- o rebuild all the tooling for building, testing, and delivering front end code with the Rails application, using modern build technology such as webpack (using webpacker), jest, and the JavaScript Testing Library
- o document all work in order to provide other current and future engineers information on how to use and extend the GraphQL API and React front end components and architecture
- o mentor, train, coach, and guide other engineers in learning Ruby, Rails, JavaScript, React, GraphQL, Apollo and the architecture and technologies used in the Kickserv product, as well as useful documentation skills, communication skills, remote team interactions, planning, estimating, and management skills

2016-2017 Contract Software Developer, Software for Good, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Provide software to enable clients to query a large datastore with natural language and return meaningful datasets.

• write anisble and shell scripts to deploy project to staging

- write training questions and entity extraction code
- o write extraction, transfer, and load scripts for external data
- o provide code review and expertise to other project members
- wrote mainly in Python
- deployments using Ansible to AWS

2013-2016 Contract Software Developer, Ackmann-Dickenson, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Contract development in the areas of Rails and JavaScript on several A-D projects.

- Pro subscriptions and e-commerce in Brewtoad
- One-button recipe ordering in Brewtoad
- Customer Onboarding
- Micro-service architecture and implementation
- Angular SPA clients for MSA backend
- Massive and complex data analysis product
- O Data ETL middle layer to provide a massive speed-up for an e-commerce website
- Lots of Ruby on Rails and JavaScript
- o Deployments using chef, puppet, and ansible to Rackspace and AWS EBS

1980-present

Various positions, Hewlett-Packard, Shopzilla, NovuHealth, BluewaterBrand.

Career as a software developer, business analyst, process and technology consultant, author, facilitator, trainer

- Web development in PHP, JavaScript, Ruby on Rails
- Software development on unix system software
- Taught relationship-based skills to engineers, managers, and senior execs.
- Consulted with various software development groups within Hewlett-Packard to improve software development capabilities
- Developed software for network management at Hewlett-Packard
- Software Quality Engineer manager of 10 engineers
- Software Quality Engineer